I have a confession to make.
لدي اعتراف.
I am addicted to adventure,
أنا مدمن مغامرات،
and as a young boy,
وعندما كنت شابًا صغيرًا،
I would rather look outside the window
كنت أفضل النظر للخارج من الشباك
at the birds in the trees and the sky
ومشاهدة الطيور على الأشجار وفي السماء
than looking at that two-dimensional
بدلًا من النظر إلى تلك السبورة ثنائية الأبعاد
chalky blackboard where time stands still
التي يتوقف عندها الزمن
and even sometimes dies.
بل في بعض الأحيان يموت.
My teachers thought there was something wrong
ظن أساتذتي بوجود مشكلة لدي
with me because I wasn't paying attention in class.
لأني لم أكن منتبه معهم في الفصل.
They didn't find anything specifically wrong with me,
ولكنهم لم يجدوا أي مشكلة بي،
other than being slightly dyslexic because I'm a lefty.
سوى القليل من صعوبات التعلم لأني أعسر.
But they didn't test for curiosity.
لكنهم لم يختبروا فضولي.
Curiosity, to me,
الفضول، بالنسبة لي،
is about our connection
هو عن اتصالنا
with the world, with the universe.
مع العالم، ومع الكون.
It's about seeing what's around that next coral head
رؤية ماذا يوجد حول ذلك الصخر المرجاني
or what's around that next tree,
أو حول تلك الشجرة،
and learning more not only about our environment
ومعرفة الكثير ليس فقط عن بيئتنا
but about ourselves.
ولكن حول أنفسنا.
Now, my dream of dreams,
والآن، حلم أحلامي،
I want to go explore the oceans of Mars,
هو رغبتي الذهاب واستكشاف المحيطات في المريخ،
but until we can go there,
ولكن إلى أن نستطيع الذهاب هناك،
I think the oceans still hold
اعتقد أن المحيطات مازالت تحمل
quite a few secrets.
العديد من الأسرار.
As a matter of fact,
وبالمناسبة،
if you take our planet as the oasis in space that it is
لو تأخذ كوكبنا كواحة في الفضاء
and dissect it into a living space,
وتقسمها كمنطقة معيشة،
the ocean represents over 3.4 billion
ستمثل المحيطات أكثر من ٣,٤ بليون
cubic kilometers of volume, within which
متر مكعب من الحجم، والذي بدورنا
we've explored less than five percent.
قمنا باستكشاف أقل من ٥٪ منه.
And I look at this, and I go, well,
وعندما أتأمل ذلك، وأذهب، حسنًا،
there are tools to go deeper, longer and further:
هناك أدوات للذهاب بشكل أعمق، وأطول وأبعد:
submarines, ROVs, even Scuba diving.
غواصات، عربات الغوص في البحار أو الغطس.
But if we're going to explore the final frontier
ولكن إذا أردنا أن نستكشف نهايات حدود
on this planet, we need to live there.
هذا الكوكب، علينا أن نعيش هناك.
We need to build a log cabin, if you will,
علينا أن نبني كوخ خشبي، إن أمكننا،
at the bottom of the sea.
في أسفل البحر.
And so there was a great curiosity in my soul
مع وجود فضولٍ كبير في روحي
when I went to go visit a TED [Prize winner]
عندما ذهبت لزيارة الحائزة على جائزة تيد
by the name of Dr. Sylvia Earle.
التي بأسم د. سيلفيا إيرل.
Maybe you've heard of her.
ربما تكونوا قد سمعتم عنها.
Two years ago, she was staked out
منذ سنتين عاشت
at the last undersea marine laboratory
في آخر مختبر تحت البحر
to try and save it,
في محاولة لإنقاذه،
to try and petition
للمحاولة وجمع التوقيعات
for us not to scrap it
لكي لا نوقفه كخردة
and bring it back on land.
ونعيده إلى اليابسة.
We've only had about a dozen or so
لما يكن لدينا سوى 12 أو نحو ذلك
scientific labs at the bottom of the sea.
من المختبرات العلمية تحت الماء.
There's only one left in the world:
ولم يتبقي سوى واحد فقط:
it's nine miles offshore
يبعد 9 أميال من الشاطئ
and 65 feet down.
وعلى عمق 65 قدم.
It's called Aquarius.
يدعي "أكواريوس."
Aquarius, in some fashion,
أكواريوس، في أحد التصاميم،
is a dinosaur,
ديناصور،
an ancient robot chained to the bottom,
إنسان آلي عتيق مربوط بسلاسل للقاع،
this Leviathan.
هذا الوحش البحري.
In other ways, it's a legacy.
بطريقة أخرى، تراث.
And so with that visit, I realized that my time is short
ولذلك أثناء هذه الزيارة، أدركت أن وقتي قصير
if I wanted to experience
إذا أردت أن أجرب
what it was like to become an aquanaut.
كيف سيصبح الأمر لو أصبحت رائد بحار.
When we swam towards this after many
حين سبحنا نحوها بعد كثير من
moons of torture and two years of preparation,
العذاب وسنتان من التحضير،
this habitat waiting to invite us
هذا المقر كان ينتظر قدومنا
was like a new home.
بدا كبيتنا الجديد.
And the point of going down to
والهدف من الغوص إليه
and living at this habitat was not to stay inside.
والحياة فيه، لم يكن البقاء بداخله.
It wasn't about living at something the size of a school bus.
لم يكن الهدف العيش في مكان بحجم حافلة مدرسية.
It was about giving us the luxury of time
الهدف هو إعطاؤنا متسعًا من الوقت
outside to wander, to explore,
للبقاء خارجه والتجول، والاستكشاف،
to understand more about this oceanic final frontier.
لفهم المزيد عن الحدود الأخيرة للمحيط.
We had megafauna come and visit us.
كانت تزورنا حيوانات بحرية ضخمة.
This spotted eagle ray is a fairly common sight in the oceans.
سمك الطباق هذا هو مشهد مألوف في المحيطات.
But why this is so important,
ولكن لماذا الأمر بهذه الأهمية،
why this picture is up,
لماذا هذه الصورة مهمة،
is because this particular animal brought his friends around,
لأن هذا الحيوان أتى بأصدقائه إلينا،
and instead of being the pelagic animals that they were,
وبدلًا من كونها الحيوانات البحرية المعتادة،
they started getting curious about us,
بدؤا الأهتمام بنا،
these new strangers that were moving into the neighborhood,
بهؤلاء الغرباء الجدد الذين انتقلوا للسكن بالجوار،
doing things with plankton.
يفعلون أشياء بالعوالق.
We were studying all sorts of animals and critters,
كنا ندرس كل أنواع الحيوانات والمخلوقات،
and they got closer and closer to us,
وبدؤا هم بالتقرب مننا أكثر وأكثر،
and because of the luxury of time,
ولأننا نملك متسعًا من الوقت،
these animals, these residents of the coral reef,
هذه الحيوانات، سكان الشعاب المرجانية،
were starting to get used to us,
بدؤا التعود علينا،
and these pelagics that normal travel through stopped.
وهذه الأسماك التي ترحل في المعتاد، توقفت.
This particular animal actually circled
هذا الحيوان الفريد ظل يتابعنا
for 31 full days during our mission.
لمدة 31 يومًا كاملًا خلال مهمتنا.
So mission 31 wasn't so much
إذن، المهمة 31 لم تهدف بالضرورة
about breaking records.
لتحطيم الأرقام القياسية.
It was about that human-ocean connection.
كانت عن التواصل بين الإنسان والمحيط.
Because of the luxury of time, we were able
ولأننا كنا نملك متسعًا من الوقت،
to study animals such as sharks and grouper
تمكننا من دراسة حيوانات كالقرش والهامور
in aggregations that we've never seen before.
في تجمعات لم نرها أبدًا من قبل.
It's like seeing dogs and cats behaving well together.
كانت كرؤية الكلاب والقطط يتعاملون بشكل جيد مع بعضهم البعض.
Even being able to commune with animals
وأصبحنا قادرين على التعايش مع حيوانات
that are much larger than us,
أكبر حجمًا بكثير منا،
such as this endangered goliath grouper
مثل الأخفس الضخم المعرض للانقارض
who only still resides in the Florida Keys.
الذي مازل يوجد في فلوريدا كيز فقط.
Of course, just like any neighbor,
بالطبع، كأي جار،
after a while, if they get tired,
بعد برهة، إذا شعروا بالتعب،
the goliath grouper barks at us,
ينبح الأخفس الضخم علينا
and this bark is so powerful
وهذا النباح كان قوى للغاية
that it actually stuns its prey before it aspirates it all
ويفترض أن تخيف فريسته قبل أن يلتهمها كلها
within a split second.
في جزء من الثانية.
For us, it's just telling us to go back
بالنسبة لنا، هم يقولون "عودوا
into the habitat and leave them alone.
إلى سكنكم واتركونا لحالنا."
Now, this wasn't just about adventure.
لم يكن ذلك فقط على سبيل المغامرة.
There was actually a serious note to it.
في الواقع كان هناك ملاحظات مهمة.
We did a lot of science, and again, because of the luxury of time,
قمنا بالكثير من العلم، ومرة أخرى لأننا كنا نملك متسعًا من الوقت،
we were able to do over three years of science
تمكننا بالقيام بأكثر من 3 سنوات من الأبحاث العلمية
in 31 days.
في 31 يوم.
In this particular case, we were using a PAM,
في هذه الحالة بالتحديد، كنا نستخدم PAM،
or, let me just see if I can get this straight,
أو بشكل أوضح،
a Pulse Amplitude Modulated Fluorometer.
Pulse Amplitude Modulated Fluorometer ترنيم بمطال النبضة.
And our scientists from FIU, MIT,
وتمكن علماؤنا في جامعات MIT و FIU
and from Northeastern
وجامعة نورث إيسترن
were able to get a gauge for what coral reefs do
من الحصول على مقياس لما تفعله الشعب المرجانية
when we're not around.
عندما لا نكون موجودين.
The Pulse Amplitude Modulated Fluorometer, or PAM,
ترنيم بمطال النبضة أو PAM،
gauges the fluorescence of corals
يقيس إشعاع الشعاب المرجانية
as it pertains to pollutants in the water
وعلاقتها بالملوثات في الماء
as well as climate change-related issues.
بالإضافة إلى المشاكل المتعلقة بالتغير المناخي.
We used all sorts of other cutting-edge tools,
استخدمنا كل أنواع الأدوات الحديثة،
such as this sonde, or what I like to call
كهذا المجس، أو ما أدعوه
the sponge proctologist, whereby the sonde
أخصائي أمراض المستقيم الإسفنجي، حيث أن المجس نفسه يجري اختبارات
itself tests for metabolism rates
حول معدل عملية التمثيل الغذائي
in what in this particular case is a barrel sponge,
لحالة الإسفنج البرميلي خاصةً
or the redwoods of the [ocean].
أو الخشب الأحمر من [المحيط].
And this gives us a much better gauge
وأعطانا هذا قياسات أقضل
of what's happening underwater
عما يحدث تحت الماء
with regard to climate change-related issues,
لما يتعلق بالتغيرات المناخية،
and how the dynamics of that
وتأثير ذلك
affect us here on land.
علينا هنا، على اليابسة.
And finally, we looked at predator-prey behavior.
وأخيرًا، راقبنا سلوك المفترس والفريسة.
And predator-prey behavior is an interesting thing,
وهو أمر مثير للاهتمام،
because as we take away some of the predators
لأننا إذا نزعنا بعض الكائنات المفترسة
on these coral reefs around the world,
من تلك الشعاب المرجانية حول العالم،
the prey, or the forage fish, act very differently.
تتصرف الأسماك بشكل مختلف للغاية.
What we realized is
ما أدركناه
not only do they stop taking care of the reef,
أن الأمر لا يتوقف عند فقدانهم الاهتمام بالعناية بالشعاب،
darting in, grabbing a little bit of algae
والاندفاع في الطحالب وانتزاعها
and going back into their homes,
ثم العودة إلى بيوتهم،
they start spreading out and disappearing
بل إنهم يبدؤون في الانتشار والاختفاء
from those particular coral reefs.
من تلك البقاع من الشعاب المرجانية.
Well, within that 31 days,
حسنًا، خلال الـ 31 يوم،
we were able to generate over 10 scientific papers
تمكننا من تأليف أكثر من 10 أوراق علمية
on each one of these topics.
حول كل من هذه المواضيع.
But the point of adventure is not only to learn,
ولكن الهدف من المغامرة ليس فقط التعلم،
it's to be able to share that knowledge with the world,
بل مشاركة تلك المعرفة مع العالم،
and with that, thanks to a couple of engineers at MIT,
وبذلك شكرًا إلى زوج من المهندسين في MIT،
we were able to use a prototype camera called the Edgertronic
تمكننا من إستخدام نموذج أولي لكاميرا تدعى إيدج-ترونيك
to capture slow-motion video,
لتصوير فيديو بالحركة البطيئة،
up to 20,000 frames per second
حتى 20,000 إطار في الثانية
in a little box
في صندوق صغير
that's worth 3,000 dollars.
يقدر ثمنه بـ 3 آلاف دولار.
It's available to every one of us.
كانت متوفرة لكل واحد مننا.
And that particular camera gives us an insight
هذه الكاميرا الفريدة أعطتنا رؤية أوضح
into what fairly common animals do
لما تفعله الحيوانات الشائعة
but we can't even see it in the blink of an eye.
ولكننا لا نستطيع رؤيته في غمضة عين.
Let me show you a quick video
دعوني أريكم فيديو قصير
of what this camera does.
لما يمكن لهذه الكاميرا فعله.
You can see the silky bubble come out
يمكنكم رؤية الفقاعات الصغيرة التى تخرج
of our hard hats.
من قبعاتنا الصلبة.
It gives us an insight
أعطتنا فهم أكبر
into some of the animals that we were sitting
للحيوانات التى كانت تعيش
right next to for 31 days
إلى جوارنا لـ 31 يومًا
and never normally would have paid attention to,
ولم نكن نلاحظها بشكل طبيعي،
such as hermit crabs.
مثل السرطان الناسك.
Now, using a cutting-edge piece of technology
الآن، بمساعدة تكونولوجيا حديثة
that's not really meant for the oceans
لم تكن مستعملة بالأساس للمحيطات
is not always easy.
لم يكن الأمر بهذه السهولة دائمًا.
We sometimes had to put the camera upside down,
أحيانا كنا نحتاج لوضع الكاميرا في وضع مقلوب،
cordon it back to the lab,
نوصلها بالمختبر،
and actually man the trigger
ويقوم إنسان حقيقي بالضغط عليها
from the lab itself.
من داخل المختبر نفسه.
But what this gives us
ولكن ما حصلنا عليه
is the foresight to look at and analyze
معلومات لمشاهدتها وتحليلها
in scientific and engineering terms
على أسس علمية وهندسية
some of the most amazing behavior
إحدى السلوكيات المدهشة التى لا تستطيع
that the human eye just can't pick up,
العين البشرية التقاطها،
such as this manta shrimp
مثل جمبري المانتا هذا
trying to catch its prey,
يحاول التقاط فريسته،
within about .3 seconds.
في خلال حوالى 0.3 ثانية.
That punch is as strong as a .22 caliber bullet,
قوة هذه اللكمة تماثل قوة رصاصة كاليبر عيار 0.22،
and if you ever try to catch a bullet
وإذا حاولت أن تلتقط الطلقة
in mid-flight with your eye, impossible.
أثناء طيرانها بعينيك، فإن الأمر مستحيل،
But now we can see things
ولكن الآن يمكننا رؤية اشياء
such as these Christmas tree worms
كهذه الديدان على شكلة شجرة الكريسماس
pulling in and fanning out
تنقبض وتندفع
in a way that the eye just can't capture,
بطريقة لا ترى بالعين المجردة،
or in this case,
أو في هذه الحالة،
a fish throwing up grains of sand.
سمكة تنفث حبيبات الرمل.
This is an actual sailfin goby,
هذه سمكة شعاعية الزعانف حقيقية،
and if you look at it in real time,
وإذا رأيتها في الحقيقة،
it actually doesn't even show its fanning motion
فلا يمكنك رؤية حركتها المروحية
because it's so quick.
لأنها سريعة للغاية.
One of the most precious gifts that we had underwater
أحد أهم المزايا التى حصلنا عليها تحت الماء
is that we had WiFi,
إننا كان لدينا إنترنت لاسلكي،
and for 31 days straight we were able to connect
ولمدة 31 يومًا كنا قادرين على الإتصال
with the world in real time from the bottom of the sea
بالعالم الخارجي من قاع البحر
and share all of these experiences.
ومشاركة كل هذه التجارب.
Quite literally right there
تحديدًا هنا
I am Skyping in the classroom
استخدم سكايب في محاضرة
with one of the six continents
مع أحد القارات الستة
and some of the 70,000 students that we connected
وبعض من الـ 70 ألف طالب
every single day to some of these experiences.
شاركنا معهم تجاربنا يومًا بيوم
As a matter of fact, I'm showing a picture that I took
في الحقيقة، إننى أريهم صورة التقتطها
with my smartphone from underwater
بهاتفي الذكي تحت الماء
of a goliath grouper laying on the bottom.
لسمك الأخفس الضخم مستقر في القاع.
We had never seen that before.
هذا شئ لم نره من قبل.
And I dream of the day
وأنا أحلم باليوم
that we have underwater cities,
الذي سيكون لدينا فيه مدنًا تحت الماء،
and maybe, just maybe, if we push the boundaries
وربما، فقط ربما، لو تخطينا حدود
of adventure and knowledge,
المغامرة والمعرفة،
and we share that knowledge with others out there,
وشاركنا المعلومات مع الآخرين،
we can solve all sorts of problems.
يمكننا حل جميع المشاكل.
My grandfather used to say,
اعتاد جدي أن يقول،
"People protect what they love."
"الناس يحمون الأشياء التي يحبونها"
My father, "How can people protect
فيرد أبي: "كيف يحمي الناس
what they don't understand?"
ما لا يفهمونه؟"
And I've thought about this my whole life.
وفكرت أنا في ذلك طوال عمري.
Nothing is impossible.
لا شئ مستحيل.
We need to dream, we need to be creative,
نحتاج أن نحلم، نحتاج أن نكون مبدعين،
and we all need to have an adventure
وجميعنا نحتاج أن نغامر
in order to create miracles in the darkest of times.
لعمل المعجزات في أحلك الأوقات.
And whether it's about climate change
وسواء أكان الأمر بخصوص التغيرات المناخية
or eradicating poverty
أم القضاء على الفقر
or giving back to future generations
أم إعطاء الأجيال القادمة
what we've taken for granted,
ما حصلنا عليه كحق مكتسب،
it's about adventure.
فالأمر مغامرة.
And who knows, maybe there will be underwater cities,
ومن يعلم، ربما سيكون هناك مدن تحت الماء،
and maybe some of you
وربما بعض منكم
will become the future aquanauts.
سيصبح رائد بحار مستقبلًا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)